[{"question":"1.The essence of positive synergy can be found in the phrase:\nA.Front of ship sink---back of ship sink\nB.There is no \"I\" in team\nC.Two heads are better than one\nD.The whole is greater than the sum of the parts\nE.If it doesn't kill you, it makes you stronger","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"The essence of positive synergy can be found in the phrase \"The whole is greater than the sum of the parts.\"","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"2.Which of the following is commonly associated with high-performing project teams?\nA.Risk taking is controlled and not allowed to jeopardize the overall project\nB.Roles and specific responsibilities are well-defined\nC.A degree of competition among team members is encouraged\nD.Mistakes are viewed as opportunities for learning\nE.All of these are associated with high-performing teams","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"To encourage risk taking and creativity, mistakes are treated as opportunities for learning rather than reasonsfor punishment.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"3.During which stage of team development do members accept that they are part of a project group but resist theconstraints that the project and the group put on their individuality?\nA.Norming\nB.Storming\nC.Performing\nD.Adjourning\nE.Forming","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"As the name suggests, this stage is marked by a high degree of internal conflict. Members accept that they arepart of a project group but resist the constraints that the project and group put on their individuality.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"4.During which stage of team development do close relationships develop and the group demonstrates cohesiveness?\nA.Norming\nB.Storming\nC.Performing\nD.Adjourning\nE.Forming","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"The norming stage is one in which close relationships develop and the group demonstrates cohesiveness.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"5.During which stage of team development is the team fully functional and accepted?\nA.Norming\nB.Storming\nC.Performing\nD.Adjourning\nE.Forming","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"In the Performing stage, the team operating structure at this point is fully functional and accepted. Group energyhas moved from getting to know each other and how the group will work together to accomplishing the projectgoals.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"6.During which stage of team development is high performance not a top priority and team member emotions run fromupbeat to depressed?\nA.Norming\nB.Storming\nC.Performing\nD.Adjourning\nE.Forming","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"For conventional work groups, performing is the last stage of their development. However, for project teams,there is a completion phase. During this stage, the team prepares for its own disbandment. High performanceis no longer a top priority. Instead attention is devoted to wrapping up the project. Responses of membersvary in this stage. Some members are upbeat, basking in the project team's accomplishments. Others may bedepressed over loss of camaraderie and friendships gained during the project's life.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"7.During which stage of team development do team members try to find out what behaviors are acceptable and whatperformance expectations are?\nA.Norming\nB.Storming\nC.Performing\nD.Adjourning\nE.Forming","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"During this initial stage the members get acquainted with each other and understand the scope of the project.They begin to establish ground rules by trying to find out what behaviors are acceptable with respect toboth the project (what role they will play, what performance expectations are) and interpersonal relations(who's really in charge). This stage is completed once members begin to think of themselves as part of agroup.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"8.Sam is the coach of a high school soccer team and has noticed that some close relationships have formed as wellas feelings of camaraderie and shared responsibilities for the team's success. Which stage of developmentis the team in?\nA.Norming\nB.Storming\nC.Performing\nD.Adjourning\nE.Forming","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"The norming stage is one in which close relationships develop and the group demonstrates cohesiveness. Feelingsof camaraderie and shared responsibility for the project are heightened. The norming phase is complete whenthe group structure solidifies and the group establishes a common set of expectations about how members shouldwork together.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"9.Roger is new-product project manager for a retail company. Recently the team has exhibited a high degree of conflictover who will control the group and how decisions will be made. Which stage of development is the team in?\nA.Norming\nB.Storming\nC.Performing\nD.Adjourning\nE.Forming","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"Members accept that they are part of a project group but resist the constraints that the project and group puton their individuality. There is conflict over who will control the group and how decisions will be made.As these conflicts are resolved, the project manager's leadership becomes accepted, and the group moves tothe next stage.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"10.Tom is managing a project team responsible for erecting a new office building. He notices that team members aretrying out different behaviors to see what is acceptable to the project and personal relations. Which stageof development is the team in?\nA.Norming\nB.Storming\nC.Performing\nD.Adjourning\nE.Forming","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"During forming stage, the members get acquainted with each other and understand the scope of the project. Theybegin to establish ground rules by trying to find out what behaviors are acceptable with respect to boththe project (what role they will play, what performance expectations are) and interpersonal relations (who'sreally in charge). This stage is completed once members begin to think of themselves as part of a group.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"11.Experience and research indicate that high-performance project teams are much more likely to develop under allthe following conditions except:\nA.Members are assigned to the project full time\nB.Members report solely to the project manager\nC.There are 10 or fewer members per team\nD.Team members are selected by their managers\nE.The project involves a compelling objective","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"See List on Page 378.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"12.In which of the following theories does the project group transition from a lower level to a higher level ofperformance about halfway through the project?\nA.Nominal Group Technique\nB.Five Stage Team Development Model\nC.Punctuated Equilibrium Model of Group Development\nD.Dysfunctional Transition Model\nE.Synergistic Transition Development Model","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"Refer to Figure 11.2 on Page 379.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"13.Which of the following are considered very important in the recruiting of project members?\nA.The budget available\nB.The importance of the project\nC.The management structure for the project team\nD.Both B and C are correct\nE.A, B, and C are all correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"The process of selecting and recruiting project members will vary across organizations. Two important factorsaffecting recruitment are the importance of the project and the management structure being used to completethe project.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"14.Which of the following is not one of the considerations that need to be factored into the project team recruitment process?\nA.Political connections\nB.Problem-solving ability\nC.Ambition, initiative, and energy\nD.High degree of technological expertise\nE.Availability","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"See list on pages 381-382.","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"15.Which of the following is an objective of the first project team meeting?\nA.Overview the project's scope and objectives\nB.Address interpersonal interaction concerns\nC.Model how the team will work together\nD.Both A and C are correct\nE.A, B, and C are all correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"There are typically three objectives project managers try to achieve during the first meeting of the projectteam. The first is to provide an overview of the project, including the scope and objectives, the generalschedule, method, and procedures. The second is to begin to address some of the interpersonal concerns capturedwith these people? The third and most important objective is to begin to model how the team is going to worktogether to complete the project.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"16.Which of the following is not one of the major issues that successful project managers must address in the early stages of a project?\nA.Relationship Decisions\nB.Managing Change Decisions\nC.Tracking Decisions\nD.Planning Decisions\nE.All of these need to be addressed","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See list on Page 383-384.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"17.Researchers have found that high performance teams will have which of the following norms?\nA.Hard work does not get in the way of having fun\nB.No information is shared outside the team unless all agree to it\nC.It is acceptable to be in trouble, but not to surprise others\nD.Both B and C are correct\nE.A, B, and C are all correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See list on page 385.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"18.All of the following have been found to be good for running effective project meetings except:\nA.Start meetings on time regardless of whether everyone is present\nB.Identify an adjournment time\nC.Thoroughly document all decisions\nD.Prepare and distribute an agenda prior to the meeting\nE.All of these are good for effective meetings","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See list on page 387.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"19.Establishing a team identity is facilitated by:\nA.Team members working in a common space\nB.Creation of a project team name\nC.Effective use of meetings\nD.Both A and B are correct\nE.A, B, and C are all correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See list on page 387-388.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"20.The essential qualities of an effective vision include all of the following except:\nA.All team members have the same vision\nB.The vision should be communicated to all\nC.The vision has to make strategic sense\nD.There should be a passion for the vision\nE.The vision should be a source of inspiration to others","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"Refer to Figure 11.4 on Page 390.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"21.Which of the following would be considered the most effective project reward?\nA.Individual member rewards\nB.Lump-sum cash award\nC.All-expenses-paid trip for team members and their families\nD.Using negative reinforcement to motivate adequate performance\nE.All of these are equally effective","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"To have more value, rewards need to have lasting significance. Many companies convert cash into vacation rewards,sometimes with corresponding time off. For example, there is one firm that rewarded a project team for gettingthe job done ahead of schedule with a four-day, all-expenses-paid trip to Walt Disney World for the members'entire families.","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"22.Individual rewards for outstanding work would not include:\nA.Letters of commendation\nB.Public recognition\nC.Desirable job assignments\nD.Making exceptions to the rules\nE.All of these can be used for individual rewards","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See list on page 393.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"23.The first step in facilitating group decision making is to:\nA.Call a meeting to discuss the problem\nB.Identify the problem\nC.Agree that there is a problem\nD.Quantify the problem\nE.Generate alternatives","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"The project manager needs to be careful not to state the problem in terms of choices (e.g., should we do X orY?). Rather the project manager should identify the underlying problem to which these alternatives and probablyothers are potential solutions. This allows group members to generate alternatives, not just choose amongthem.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"24.Strategies to manage dysfunctional conflict do not include _____ the conflict.\nA.Control\nB.Arbitrate\nC.Mediate\nD.Accept\nE.Encourage","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See list on page 398.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"25.The biggest challenge to managing a virtual project team is:\nA.Getting reports and technical information communicated\nB.Developing trust\nC.Establishing effective patterns of communication\nD.Both B and C are correct\nE.A, B, and C are all correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"Two of the biggest challenges involved in managing a virtual project team are developing trust and effectivepatterns of communication.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"26.Which of the following is not one of the steps in facilitating group decision making?\nA.Identifying the problem\nB.Analyzing the situation\nC.Generating alternatives\nD.Reaching a decision\nE.Follow-up","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"See list on pages 394-395.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"27.During the delivery phase of a project's life cycle, the most significant source of conflict is:\nA.Schedules\nB.Priorities\nC.Technical\nD.Procedures\nE.Costs","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"During the delivery phase, schedules continue as the biggest source of conflict as schedule slippages make itmore difficult to meet target completion dates.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"28.Two of the biggest challenges involved in managing a virtual project team are:\nA.The language barriers and time management\nB.Time management and developing trust\nC.The language barriers and developing effective patterns of communication\nD.Developing trust and effective patterns of communication\nE.Time management and developing effective patterns of communication","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"Two of the biggest challenges involved in managing a virtual project team are developing trust and effectivepatterns of communication.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"29.Symptoms of groupthink include:\nA.The team thinking it is invincible\nB.Opinions of those outside the team are considered to be irrelevant\nC.Critical thinking disappears\nD.Pressure is applied to any dissenter\nE.All of these are symptoms of groupthink","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See list on page 404.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"30.Which of the following are ways to improve the performance of low-priority projects?\nA.Creating a large time investment in the form of a lengthy meeting\nB.Interject as much fun as possible into the project\nC.Make the benefits of the project as real as possible to the team members\nD.Both B and C are correct\nE.A, B, and C are all correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"One project manager advocated orchestrating a large \"time\" investment upfront on such projects—either in theform of a lengthy meeting or a significant early assignment. He viewed this as a form of down payment thatmembers would forfeit if they didn't carry the project to completion. Others emphasize interjecting as muchfun into activities as possible. Her rituals discussed under building team identity come into play. Peoplebecome committed because they enjoy working together on the project. One project manager even confided thatthe perfect attendance at her project meetings was due primarily to the quality of the doughnuts she provided.Another strategy is to make the benefits of the project as real to the team members as possible. One projectmanager escalated commitment to a mandated accidents prevention task force by bringing accident victims toa project meeting.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"31.Which of the following is not one of the most significant sources of conflict during the project definition phase?\nA.Priorities\nB.Administrative procedures\nC.Schedule\nD.Workforce\nE.Costs","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"During project definition, the most significant sources of conflict are priorities, administrative procedures,schedule, and workforce.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"32.Which of the following is not one of the most significant sources of conflict during the project planning phase?\nA.Priorities\nB.Procedures\nC.Schedule\nD.Technical requirements\nE.Costs","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"During the planning phase, the chief source of conflict remains priorities, followed by schedules, procedures,and technical requirements.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"33.Which of the following is not one of the most significant sources of conflict during the project execution phase?\nA.Priorities\nB.Staff issues\nC.Schedule slippage\nD.Technical problems\nE.All of these are significant sources of conflict","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"During the execution phase, friction arises over schedule slippage, technical problems, and staff issues. Milestonesbecome more difficult to meet because of accumulating schedule slippages.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"34.Which of the following is not one of the tips for alleviating communication problems of virtual teams?\nA.Include face-to-face time if at all possible\nB.Keep team members informed on how well the overall project is going\nC.Share the pain\nD.Establish clear norms and protocols for surfacing assumptions and conflicts\nE.Establish a code of conduct to avoid delays","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"See list on pages 402-403.Fill in the Blank Questions","difficulty":"Fill in the Blank Questions"},{"question":"35.________ occurs when the whole is less than the sum of its parts.","type":"fill-in","answer":"Negative synergy","help":"Negative synergy occurs when the whole is less than the sum of the parts.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"36.During the ________ stage of group development, there is conflict over who will control the group and how decisionswill be made.","type":"fill-in","answer":"storming","help":"As the name suggests, this stage is marked by a high degree of internal conflict. Members accept that they arepart of a project group but resist the constraints that the project and group put on their individuality.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"37.During the ________ stage of group development, the members try to find out what behaviors are acceptable tothe team and individual team members.","type":"fill-in","answer":"forming","help":"During this initial stage the members get acquainted with each other and understand the scope of the project.They begin to establish ground rules by trying to find out what behaviors are acceptable with respect toboth the project (what role they will play, what performance expectations are) and interpersonal relations(who's really in charge). This stage is completed once members begin to think of themselves as part of agroup.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"38.During the ________ stage of group development, the team prepares for its own disbandment.","type":"fill-in","answer":"adjourning","help":"For conventional work groups, performing is the last stage of their development. However, for project teams,there is a completion phase. During this stage, the team prepares for its own disbandment. High performanceis no longer a top priority. Instead attention is devoted to wrapping up the project. Responses of membersvary in this stage. Some members are upbeat, basking in the project team's accomplishments. Others may bedepressed over loss of camaraderie and friendships gained during the project's life.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"39.During the ________ stage of group development, close relationships develop and the group demonstrates cohesiveness.","type":"fill-in","answer":"norming","help":"The norming stage is one in which close relationships develop and the group demonstrates cohesiveness. Feelingsof camaraderie and shared responsibility for the project are heightened. The norming phase is complete whenthe group structure solidifies and the group establishes a common set of expectations about how members shouldwork together.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"40.During the ________ stage of group development, the team is fully functional and working together to accomplishingthe project goals.","type":"fill-in","answer":"performing","help":"In the Performing stage, the team operating structure at this point is fully functional and accepted. Group energyhas moved from getting to know each other and how the group will work together to accomplishing the projectgoals.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"41.The ________ suggests that about midway through a project the team transitions into a different behavior patternmore focused on the successful completion of the project.","type":"fill-in","answer":"Punctuated Equilibrium Model of Group Development","help":"Refer to Figure 11.2 on Page 379.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"42.Experienced project managers stress the importance of ________ rather than appointing team members.","type":"fill-in","answer":"asking for volunteers","help":"Experienced project managers stress the importance of asking for volunteers. However, this desirable step oftentimesis outside the manager's control. Still, the value of having team members volunteer for the project as opposedto being assigned cannot be overlooked. Agreeing to work on the project is the first step toward buildingpersonal commitment to the project. Such commitment will be essential to maintain motivation when the projecthits hard times and extra effort is required.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"43.Too often when constrained by time, project managers try to accomplish too much during the first meeting, ratherthan use the ________ principle and not create information overload.","type":"fill-in","answer":"keep it simple stupid (KISS)","help":"Many organizations do not have the luxury of holding elaborate retreats. In other cases the scope of projectand level of involvement of different participants does not warrant such an investment of time. In thesecases, the key operating principle should be KISS (keep it simple stupid!) Too often when constrained bytime, project managers try to accomplish too much during the first meeting; in doing so, issues do not getfully resolved, and members come away with an information headache.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"44._______ are often considered anathema to productivity, yet they are critical to the success of any project.","type":"fill-in","answer":"Meetings","help":"Meetings are often considered an anathema to productivity, but this does not have to be the case. The most commoncomplaint is that meetings last too long. Establishing an agenda and adjournment time helps participantsbudget discussion time and provides a basis for expediting the proceedings.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"45.Symbolic actions at the project level can contribute to a unique team subculture are called ________.","type":"fill-in","answer":"team rituals","help":"Team rituals such as symbolic actions at the project level can contribute to a unique team subculture.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"46.In the Snapshot from Practice involving the Tallahassee Democrat newspaper, the key turning point was the handlingof an advertisement, eventually known as the ________ that had been sent to the newspaper over a fax machine.","type":"fill-in","answer":"rat fax","help":"A key turning point came when one member produced what became known as \"the rat tracks fax\" and told the storybehind it. It turns out a sloppily prepared ad arrived through a fax machine looking like \"a rat had runacross the page.\" Yet the ad passed through the hands of seven employees and probably would have been printedif it had not been totally unreadable.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"47.The development of _________________ is a common device for making a team more tangible.","type":"fill-in","answer":"project team name","help":"The development of a team name such as the \"A-Team\" or \"Casey's Crusaders\" is a common device for making a teammore tangible.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"48.Expressing the design concept of a new car as a \"pocket rocket\" (a sports car in the mid-price range) is an exampleof a simplified ________.","type":"fill-in","answer":"vision","help":"For example, the vision for a new car could be expressed as a \"pocket rocket.\" Compare this vision with the moretraditional product description—\"a sports car in the midprice range.\" The \"pocket rocket\" vision providesa much clearer picture of what the final product should be.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"49.Project managers are responsible for managing the ________ that encourage team performance and extra effort.","type":"fill-in","answer":"reward systems","help":"Project managers are responsible for managing the reward system that encourages team performance and extra effort.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"50.The use of 6:30 A.M. meetings to get a project back on schedule is an example of ______ reinforcement to motivateproject performance.","type":"fill-in","answer":"negative","help":"The project manager does not have direct authority over many key people, especially the contractors from theother companies. They do, however, have the freedom to convene meetings at his convenience. So the projectmanager will institute daily \"coordination meetings,\" which were required of all the principals involved,the project manager announced that the next meeting was canceled, and no further sunrise meetings were everscheduled.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"51.________ should be used when strong commitment to a decision is needed and there is a low probability of acceptanceif the decision were to be made by one person.","type":"fill-in","answer":"Group decision making","help":"Group decision making should be used when it will improve the quality of important decisions. This is often thecase with complex problems that require the input of a variety of different specialists. Group decision makingshould also be used when strong commitment to the decision is needed and there is a low probability of acceptanceif only one person makes the decision.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"52.When the manager intervenes and tries to negotiate a resolution by using reasoning and persuasion, suggestingalternatives and the like the Project Manager is trying to ___________.","type":"fill-in","answer":"mediate the conflict","help":"The manager intervenes and tries to negotiate a resolution by using reasoning and persuasion, suggesting alternativesand the like.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"53.In the ________ approach to managing conflict, the manager imposes a solution to the conflict after listeningto each party.","type":"fill-in","answer":"arbitrate the conflict","help":"The manager imposes a solution to the conflict after listening to each party. The goal is not to decide who winsbut to have the project win. In doing so, it is important to seek a solution that allows each party to saveface; otherwise the decision may provide only momentary relief.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"54.In a ________ project team the members are geographically situated so that they may seldom meet face-to-faceas a team.","type":"fill-in","answer":"virtual","help":"A virtual project team in where the team members are geographically situated so that they may seldom, if ever,meet face-to-face as a team.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"55.___________ refers to whether a team has direct influence over the problem that needs to be resolved.","type":"fill-in","answer":"Ownership","help":"Ownership refers to whether the team has direct influence over the issue. For example, a team probably has littleinfluence over delivery of contracted supplies, but team members do control how quickly they inform eachother of sudden changes in plans.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"56.When a project team gets things done without having to go through normal protocols of the parent organization,it may fall into the ____________.","type":"fill-in","answer":"bureaucratic bypass syndrome","help":"Project teams are often licensed to get things done without having to go through normal protocols of the parentorganization. Bypassing bureaucratic channels is appealing and invigorating. However, if bypassing becomesa way of life, it results in the rejection of bureaucratic policies and procedures, which provide the gluefor the overall organization.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"57.Project managers should encourage ___________ conflict.","type":"fill-in","answer":"functional","help":"If the team appears to be suffering from groupthink, then the project manager can encourage functional conflictby playing a devil's advocate role to encourage dissent or using a structured problem solving approach likethe nominal group technique.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"58.Project managers should manage ___________ conflict.","type":"fill-in","answer":"dysfunctional","help":"Project managers should recognize that conflict is an inevitable and even a desirable part of project work; thekey is to encourage functional conflict and manage dysfunctional conflict.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"59.In order to match technology to the communication need, 3M developed guidelines to be used on __________ projects.","type":"fill-in","answer":"distributed or virtual","help":"A major challenge for managing a virtual project team is to establish effective patterns of communication. E-mailand faxes are great for communicating facts—but not the feelings behind the facts; nor do they allow forreal-time communication. Conference calls and project chat rooms can help, but they also have their limitations.Videoconferencing is a significant improvement over nonvisual electronic forms of communication. Still, itis a very expensive medium, and realtime interaction is available on only the most advanced and expensivesystems. The maxim is match technology to the communication need.True / False Questions","difficulty":"True / False Questions"},{"question":"60.Synergy can be both negative as well as positive.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"The essence of positive synergy can be found in the phrase \"The whole is greater than the sum of the parts.\"Conversely, negative synergy occurs when the whole is less than the sum of the parts.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"61.There is a high degree of internal conflict in the forming stage of team development.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"During this initial stage the members get acquainted with each other and understand the scope of the project.They begin to establish ground rules by trying to find out what behaviors are acceptable with respect toboth the project (what role they will play, what performance expectations are) and interpersonal relations(who's really in charge). This stage is completed once members begin to think of themselves as part of agroup.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"62.The storming stage of team development is completed once members begin to think of themselves as part of a group.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"Members accept that they are part of a project group but resist the constraints that the project and group puton their individuality. There is conflict over who will control the group and how decisions will be made.As these conflicts are resolved, the project manager's leadership becomes accepted, and the group moves tothe next stage.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"63.The performing stage of team development is characterized by the development of close relationships and groupcohesiveness.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"In the Performing stage, the team operating structure at this point is fully functional and accepted. Group energyhas moved from getting to know each other and how the group will work together to accomplishing the projectgoals.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"64.The norming stage of team development is complete when the group establishes a common set of expectations abouthow members should work together.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"The norming stage is one in which close relationships develop and the group demonstrates cohesiveness. Feelingsof camaraderie and shared responsibility for the project are heightened. The norming phase is complete whenthe group structure solidifies and the group establishes a common set of expectations about how members shouldwork together.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"65.Regardless of the type of work group, the adjourning stage of team development is the final stage.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"For conventional work groups, performing is the last stage of their development. However, for project teams,there is a completion phase. During this stage, the team prepares for its own disbandment. High performanceis no longer a top priority. Instead attention is devoted to wrapping up the project. Responses of membersvary in this stage. Some members are upbeat, basking in the project team's accomplishments. Others may bedepressed over loss of camaraderie and friendships gained during the project's life.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"Refer to Figure 11.2 on Page 379.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"67.A project manager should always look for people with good problem-solving ability.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"If the project is complex and fuzzy, then a manager wants people who are good at working under uncertainty andhave strong problem identification and solving skills. These same people are likely to be bored and lessproductive working on straightforward projects that go by the book.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"68.A project manager should be wary of people who know too much about a specific technology.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"Managers should be wary of people who know too much about a specific technology. They may be technology buffswho like to study but have a hard time settling down and doing the work.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"69.Co-location of team members, team names, and team rituals are common vehicles for establishing a team identity.TRUE\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Social Network Building","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"70.A project vision is an image a project team holds in common about how the project will look upon completion,how they will work together, and how customers will accept the project.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Just as corporate rituals help establish the unique identity of a firm, similar symbolic actions at the projectlevel can contribute to a unique team subculture.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"71.Everyone on the project team should have the same vision of the project.FALSE","difficulty":"71.Everyone on the project team should have the same vision of the project.FALSE"},{"question":"Refer to Figure 11.4 on Page 390.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"72.Most project managers advocate the use of group rewards rather than individual rewards.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"To have more value, rewards need to have lasting significance. Many companies convert cash into vacation rewards,sometimes with corresponding time off. For example, there is one firm that rewarded a project team for gettingthe job done ahead of schedule with a four-day, all-expenses-paid trip to Walt Disney World for the members'entire families.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"73.Lump-sum cash bonuses are the preferred group reward for project teams.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"To have more value, rewards need to have lasting significance. Many companies convert cash into vacation rewards,sometimes with corresponding time off. For example, there is one firm that rewarded a project team for gettingthe job done ahead of schedule with a four-day, all-expenses-paid trip to Walt Disney World for the members'entire families.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"74.Letters of commendation, public recognition for outstanding work, and desirable job assignments are the preferredtypes of individual rewards.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"See list on page 393.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"75.Group decision making should be used when strong commitment to the decision is needed and there is a low probabilityof acceptance if only one person makes the decision.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Group decision making should be used when it will improve the quality of important decisions. This is often thecase with complex problems that require the input of a variety of different specialists. Group decision makingshould also be used when strong commitment to the decision is needed and there is a low probability of acceptanceif only one person makes the decision.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"76.A project manager should identify a problem in terms of its alternate solutions so that team members can moreeasily reach a decision on how to solve the problem.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"The project manager needs to be careful not to state the problem in terms of choices (e.g., should we do X orY?). Rather the project manager should identify the underlying problem to which these alternatives and probablyothers are potential solutions. This allows group members to generate alternatives, not just choose amongthem.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"77.Team members can be upset and dissatisfied with conflict, but as long as the disagreement furthers the objectivesof the project, then the conflict is functional.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Members can be upset and dissatisfied with the interchange, but as long as the disagreement furthers the objectivesof the project, then the conflict is functional. Project managers should recognize that conflict is an inevitableand even a desirable part of project work; the key is to encourage functional conflict and manage dysfunctionalconflict.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"78.A project manager arbitrates conflict by intervening and attempting to negotiate a resolution by using reasoningand persuasion, suggesting alternatives and the like.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"The manager intervenes and tries to negotiate a resolution by using reasoning and persuasion, suggesting alternativesand the like.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"79.Groupthink refers to the tendency of members in highly cohesive groups to lose their critical evaluative capabilitiesresulting in quick decision making with little consideration of alternatives.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Groupthink appears when pressures for conformity are combined with an illusion of invincibility to suspend criticaldiscussion of decisions. As a result decisions are made quickly with little consideration of alternatives;often the practice leads to fiascoes that, after the fact, appear totally improbable.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Project Team PitfallsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"80.Two of the biggest challenges involved in managing a virtual project team are developing trust and effectivepatterns of communication.TRUE","difficulty":"TRUE"},{"question":"Two of the biggest challenges involved in managing a virtual project team are developing trust and effectivepatterns of communication.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Managing Virtual Project TeamsLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"81.\"Going native\" is the ability that some project teams have to bypass the normal policies and procedures thateveryone in the organization is supposed to follow.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"Bureaucratic bypass syndrome occurs when project teams are often licensed to get things done without having togo through normal protocols of the parent organization. Bypassing bureaucratic channels is appealing andinvigorating. However, if bypassing becomes a way of life, it results in the rejection of bureaucratic policiesand procedures, which provide the glue for the overall organization.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Project Team PitfallsLevel: Easy","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"82.In order to match technology to the communication need, IBM developed a set of guidelines to be used on theirvirtual projects.FALSE","difficulty":"FALSE"},{"question":"A major challenge for managing a virtual project team is to establish effective patterns of communication. E-mailand faxes are great for communicating facts—but not the feelings behind the facts; nor do they allow forreal-time communication. Conference calls and project chat rooms can help, but they also have their limitations.Videoconferencing is a significant improvement over nonvisual electronic forms of communication. Still, itis a very expensive medium, and realtime interaction is available on only the most advanced and expensivesystems. The maxim is match technology to the communication need. 3M did this for their virtual projects.\nAACSB: Reflective Thinking\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Managing Virtual Project TeamsLevel: EasyShort Answer Questions","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"83.Identify the four major areas for establishing ground rules on how the project team will operate.","difficulty":"83.Identify the four major areas for establishing ground rules on how the project team will operate."},{"question":"1. Planning decisions, 2. Tracking decisions, 3. Managing change decisions, and 4. Relationship decisions.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"84.Identify and briefly discuss the four elements to establishing a team identity.","difficulty":"84.Identify and briefly discuss the four elements to establishing a team identity."},{"question":"1. Effective use of meetings, 2. Co-location of team members, 3. Create a project team name, and 4. Team rituals.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"85.Identify the four requirements for an effective project vision.","difficulty":"85.Identify the four requirements for an effective project vision."},{"question":"1. Communicate, 2. Strategic sense, 3. Passion, and 4. Inspires others.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"86.Identify and briefly discuss the four types of individual rewards recommended for project team members.","difficulty":"86.Identify and briefly discuss the four types of individual rewards recommended for project team members."},{"question":"1. Letters of commendation, 2. Public recognition for outstanding work, 3. Job assignments, and 4. Flexibility.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"87.Identify and briefly discuss the four major steps in facilitating the group decision making process.","difficulty":"87.Identify and briefly discuss the four major steps in facilitating the group decision making process."},{"question":"1. Problem identification, 2. Generate alternatives, 3. Reach a decision, and 4. Follow-up.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"88.What is functional conflict and why should it be encouraged?","difficulty":"88.What is functional conflict and why should it be encouraged?"},{"question":"As long as disagreements further the objectives of the project, then conflict is functional. It should be encouragedbecause honest professional differences of opinion often will lead to the best solutions. The challenge isto keep it from becoming dysfunctional.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"89.Identify the five strategies to manage conflict.","difficulty":"89.Identify the five strategies to manage conflict."},{"question":"1. Mediate the conflict, 2. Arbitrate the conflict, 3. Control the conflict, 4. Accept the conflict, and 5. Eliminatethe conflict.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Building High-Performance Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"90.What is a virtual project team?","difficulty":"90.What is a virtual project team?"},{"question":"A virtual project team is one in which the team members are geographically situated so that they may seldom,if ever, meet face-to-face as a team. Electronic communications such as the Internet, e-mail, and teleconferencingare the primary means of communication.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Managing Virtual Project TeamsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"91.What is meant by the term groupthink and identify four symptoms?","difficulty":"91.What is meant by the term groupthink and identify four symptoms?"},{"question":"Groupthink refers to the tendency of members in highly cohesive groups to lose their critical evaluative capabilitiesresulting in quick decision making with little consideration of alternatives. Symptoms include 1. illusionof invulnerability, 2. whitewash of critical thinking, 3. negative stereotypes of outsiders, and 4. directpressure.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: SynthesisLearning Objective: Project Team PitfallsLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"92.From the perspective of project management, what does the term going native reference?","difficulty":"92.From the perspective of project management, what does the term going native reference?"},{"question":"The customer's interest takes precedence over the parent organization's interest, leading to scope creep andopen defiance of corporate policy and interests.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Project Team PitfallsLevel: Medium","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"93.What is the bureaucratic bypass syndrome and why is it to be avoided?","difficulty":"93.What is the bureaucratic bypass syndrome and why is it to be avoided?"},{"question":"Project teams are often licensed to get things done without having to go through normal protocols of the parentorganization. If bypassing the normal channels becomes a way of life, it results in rejecting policies andprocedures. This may alienate other workers who must follow protocol and eventually may cause them to findways to thwart the project team.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: ComprehensionLearning Objective: Project Team PitfallsLevel: Difficult","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"94.Identify and briefly describe the four common pitfalls that project teams may be subjected to.","difficulty":"94.Identify and briefly describe the four common pitfalls that project teams may be subjected to."},{"question":"1. groupthink, 2. bureaucratic bypass syndrome, 3. team infatuation, and 4. going native.\nAACSB: Analytic\nBloom's: KnowledgeLearning Objective: Project Team PitfallsLevel: Difficult11-1","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"","difficulty":""}]